# 大爷师父坐好 咱们出发
Da Ye and master please buckle up! Let’s go!
# 今天是老饭骨团建
Today is the Lao Fan Gu Team Building date!
# 目的地密云
We are heading to Miyun District.
# 二伯这次团建你有什么打算
Er Bai, what’s your plan for team building?
# 团建 我也第一次团建
Team Building. It’s my first time too.
# 我这心里还没底儿呢 大爷
I am not so confident about our plan, Da Ye.
# 在这还得宣布一下
We should make an announcement here.
# 我们网友粉丝们 还有小饭骨们
Our fans on the internet, and Xiao Fan Gu.
# 为了这次把团建搞好
In order to organize the team building activities well,
# 我和二伯一人带了一本老书
Er Bai and I brought an old book
# 过去都是言传身教
In the past, we were taught by examples
# 所以就是靠书本
Which are mainly from books
# 因为过去老的菜谱
Because the old recipes…
# 全是以文字来表达
…are recorded by words
# 读懂了以后你才能把这菜做得好
One can only make a perfect dish if one truly understands the words
# 具体什么书
But which books exactly?
# 等我们到了团建的现场
Let’s wait till we reach the team building activity site…
# 我会给大家展示的
...to show them to everyone
# 不是展示 还要做菜
Not just show, but cook
# 把那些有故事有情节的老菜
We are revealing the traditional dishes with interesting stories behind…
# 告诉我们的小饭骨
… to our Xiao Fan Gu…
# 和我们的粉丝朋友们
… and our fans
# 二伯一句话 一句话啊
Er Bai, we are running out of time.
# 就一句了
Just one more word
# 其实啊 大爷您知道么
Actually, do you know, Da Ye
# 我虽然老书不多
Although I don’t have many old books, …
# 但是我觉得我带的书的意义
…the meaning behind the books I brought…
# 意义很大
.. is huge.
# 咱们距离还有一段路程
We are still a few miles away
# 你们先吃点小花碗
You guys can eat some Xiaohuawan…
# 先垫一垫吧 可以
…so that you won’t be too hungry. Ok.
# 小花碗
Xiaohuawan
# 想吃么
Wanna eat it?
# 这边雪不小啊
The snow is quite heavy
# 北边的雪比市里的（大）
Much heavier than that in the northern part of the city
# 市里没怎么下
There isn’t much snow in the city
# 这小花碗吃了
We’ve finished eating the Xiaohuawan
# 还有什么好吃的啊
Is there anything else we could try?
# 大爷您别着急 咱们到了地方
Don’t worry, Da Ye. When we arrive at the place, …
# 咱们把咱们的大菜拿出来
…we will have the grand dishes
# 佛跳墙在那备着呢
Such as Fo Tiao Qiang.
# 亮子 我们期待着啊
Liang Zi, we are looking forward to it.
# 你好好开车
Focus on driving, please.
# 我和二伯准备要睡了
Er Bai and I plan to take a nap.
# 知道今天团建要干嘛么
Do you know what we are gonna do at Team Building Day?
# 团建不是喝酒么
Team Building is about drinking, right?
# 不是
Nah.
# 大爷二伯说 要给你们上一课
Da Ye and Er Bai said that they are gonna host a culinary session for you.
# 一般的上一课就是
Well, having such a session usually means...
# 可能犯错误了
…one might have made some mistakes.
# 晕车的隋哥已经迷茫了
Brother Sui gets carsick and looks confused.
# 北国风光 千里冰封 万里雪飘
The North country scene: A hundred leagues locked in ice; A thousand leagues of whirling snow.
# 看看 看看
Look, Look
# 到了
We are here.
# 老饭骨来啦
Lao Fan Gu is coming!
# 你不能这么说 老饭骨进村啦
You can’t say that. Lao Fan Gu arrived at the village!
# 我们这次带来了老书
We brought some old books this time
# 也带来了老菜
As well as some traditional dishes.
# 我先说说我这个老菜
Let me talk about mine first.
# 这本书是我师父编写的
This book is written by my master
# 淮扬菜部分
on the Huaiyang Cuisine.
# 是北京饭店
The book is the second book of Beijing Restaurant…
# 在建国以来的第二本书
…since the founding of the country.
# 这是1984年出的
This was published in 1984.
# 这本书是1988年我写的
I wrote this book in 1988.
# 二伯那书你看看
Look at Er Bai’s book.
# 显得比我这陈旧点
That looks a bit older than mine.
# 刚强那是哪年的
Gangqiang, which year was that?
# 1974年12月
December of 1974.
# 北京市第一服务局 我照一下
(published by)Beijing First Service Bureau. Let me take a picture.
# 那时候还没有旅游局呢
At that time, there is not even the Beijing Tourism Bureau.
# 这是我师父上学的时候
This was when my master was in school.
# 这两本都是
Both books were
# 1973年5月
（published） on May of 1973.
# 你看这个书为什么
Why are these books...
# 它有传承的意义 你看
…meaningful to be passed on? Look, …
# 无意当中 我翻出一个东西
… I accidentally found one item…
# 这是我当年随便写的一个东西
… a random note I made …
# 当厨师长的时候 写了这些东西
… when I was the head chef …
# 料单 这肯定是绝版了
Ingredient lists. Oh this must be an exhausted edition.
# 其实你看一张破纸 小便条
Actually look, it’s just a piece of torn paper, or a sticker note.
# 但是非常珍贵
Nevertheless it is very precious.
# 所以说这张纸是我
So this note is my …
# 我跟你说
I will be honest with you,
# 我看到这张纸我快流泪了
I am almost in tears when I saw this note.
# 因为40年都过去了
Because it has been 40 years,…
# 这是留给我唯一的纪念的东西
… and this is the only meaningful souvenir left for me.
# 过去出菜谱没有画片 图案
The recipes in the past came with no picture or diagram…
# 基本都是文字
… but mainly words
# 但是每个文字写得非常清晰
Yet each word was clearly written
# 每次搞国宴 我师父都是一支笔
Every time hosting a national fest, our master has a budget in his mind
# 你要作为下边分派的
He always made sure the work is planned and delegated well…
# 保证最后不会亏 也不会剩很多
… so that in the end, he is neither losing money nor creating much waste
# 当我拜这师父的时候
When I took apprenticeship under my master, …
# 很多老师傅就告诉我了
… many experienced chefs told me that…
# 说 你一定要把你师父
.. that you have to…
# 这门手艺学下来
… master the skills from your master…
# 我师父原来所传承的一个老菜
One traditional dish inherited by my master…
# 叫宝石虾球
… is called Shrimp Balls with Gems.
# 我把宝石虾球这个菜
Let me discuss this dish...
# 也给大家念叨念叨
… with everyone.
# 宝石虾球
Shrimp Balls with Gems
# 原料
Ingredient list
# 一 主料
One, main ingredients
# 大虾肉 500克 肥膘肉100克
Shrimp meat 500 g, pork fat 100 g
# 也就是说
That is to say
# 一斤虾肉要搁二两肥膘
1 jin (500g) shrimp meat pairs with 2 liang (100g) pork fat
# 这个配比数就出来了
This is the ratio
# 杨兵你看一下书
Yang Bing, take a look at the book
# 是不是500克（虾肉）
Is it 500 g shrimp meat…
# 放100克肥膘呢
…with 100 g pork fat?
# 上面写到了
It says, …
# 二 配料
Second, accessory ingredients
# 豌豆粒50克 冬菇25克
Green pea 50 g, winter mushroom （shiitake） 25 g
# 胡萝卜100克
Carrots 100g
# 宝石虾球为什么叫宝石呢
Why there are gems in shrimp ball?
# 今天先看看
Let’s take a closer look
# 这叫玛瑙 五彩缤纷了啊
This is “agate”, then more colors
# 翡翠 白玉
Jade (green), white jade
# 你看我都知道了
See I know them all
# 这叫什么呢  这黑宝石
What is this called? Black gem, maybe?
# 琥珀
No, amber
# 前面是叫粗加工
In the first part we do some rough processing
# 后边开始细加工
Then we focus on details
# 第一个过程书上怎么写的
What does the book say on the first step?
# 先把虾肉弄干净
First, clean the shrimp meat
# 然后铺开给剁成馅 虾蓉
Then spread and chopped the meat into sticky fillings, or shrimp paste
# 肥膘切成粒
Chop pork fat into pieces
# 一字不差
The exact word
# 葱切段姜切片
Then cut green onions into sections, and slice some ginger
# 加料酒 制成葱姜酒水
Add Chinese cooking wine to create green-onion-ginger-wine extract
# 加葱姜酒水 白胡椒粉 盐
Add in this extract, and white pepper power, salt
# 味精 蛋清 淀粉
MSG, egg white, starch
# 先把这搅上劲儿 是吧
Stir this well when you feel some resistance
# 这很快 说起就是三分钟
This won’t take long. About 3 minutes.
# 打馅多的时候就要摔馅
If one prepares more fillings, one needs to beat it
# 你看它有劲了
Look as it gains strong gluten structure
# 就说明它这盐就OK了
This suggests that the salt is enough
# 重量越来越重了
It seems to be stronger
# 好了
ok
# 将各种主配料合在一起
We can mix the main and accessory ingredients
# 翡翠 珍珠 玛瑙 琥珀五色宝石
Jade, White pearl/jade, agate, amber
# 搅拌上劲 挤成虾球
Stir it till the gluten is strong. Push the paste out from your palm to form shrimp balls.
# 将挤好的虾球下锅
Now the shrimps are in the pot
# 用小火沁炸熟
Low heat to have the balls fully cooked
# 过去老师傅讲
Experienced chefs once said in the past
# 炸这东西什么叫熟了
How could one tell the food is thoroughly fried?
# 浮起即熟
When it floats, it is cooked.
# 漂亮 一般我们过去这种炸的菜
Beautiful. When we fried such food in the past, …
# 要不就要炸的焦焦的 沁炸法
… we either need to fry it to a burnt color, call it “Qing Zha Technique”
# 这要吃嫩嫩的 低温油温
For this, we want to have a tender texture, so instead, we fry the food in oil with low heat
# 虾球浮起 捞出控油 装入盘中即可
When the shrimp balls float, scoop them out to drain extra oil, then place them on the plate to serve
# 你看这个颜色 安逸
Look at this color, soothing
# 三 特点
Third, characteristics
# 虾嫩味鲜
The shrimp is tender and xian (umami)
# 各色配料犹如
The variety of ingredients remind people of…
# 珊瑚 翡翠 琥珀 玛瑙 水晶之类
… a bunch of gems like coral, jade, amber, agate, crystal, etc.
# 因此得名宝石虾球
Thus, it has the name of “Shrimp Balls with Gems”
# 大爷讲这个宝石虾球
That’s it on Da Ye’s introduction of Shrimp Balls with Gems
# 就到此为止
# 二伯有一道好菜
Now we turn to Er Bai…
# 也是传统老菜
… who is going to introduce another traditional dish from the old times…
# 没人鼓掌 鼓掌
Claps your hands everyone~
# 什么老菜
Which traditional dish?
# 实际这道菜呢
Actually, this dish…
# 说是简单 你看 豆瓣鱼
… sounds quite simple: Douban Fish.
# 豆瓣鱼是我师父的传承
Douban Fish is the inheritance of my master.
# 我先念一段烹饪的理解
Let me share a piece of understanding for cooking.
# 就是我上学的时候
When I was in school, …
# 老师上的第一堂课
… in the first class …
# 记得特别清楚 烹饪是什么
…I remembered very clearly about “what is culinary art”.
# 烹饪学是研究食物原料的性质
Culinary art is the study on the properties of the food materials,…
# 刀技切配 烹调方法
… the knife skills, pairing techniques, cooking methods,
# 和菜肴的色香味形
… the color, smell, taste, shape of the dish,…
# 以及如何保护
… and how to protect…
# 其营养价值的一门科学
… the nutritional value of the food material.
# 可能你们都在岗位上
Maybe you are already comfortable in your role,
# 都是总厨 都是老板
Maybe you are all head chef, or boss/owner,
# 手艺再高超
But no matter how good you are at your skills,
# 我也希望你们
I hope you…
# 老饭骨的传承人 不要偏离了方向
… who are the heirs of Lao Fan Gu would not deviate from the focus of “culinary art”.
# 这是我跟大爷的一点希望
This is an expectation from Da Ye and I.
# 下面我就把豆瓣鱼的要求
Next, I will read the instructions of making Douban Fish…
# 一字不落的给念一遍
…in its exact word.
# 豆瓣鱼
Douban Fish
# 第一是原料
First, raw ingredients
# 主料 鲜鱼1尾 什么鱼都可以
Main ingredients: fresh fish 1 count (whatever fish you like)
# 第二是调料
Then, seasoning
# 调料是花生油 葱姜蒜
Peanut oil, green onion, ginger, garlic
# 豆瓣酱 酱油 醋
Doubanjiang, soy sauce, vinegar
# 糖 料酒 味精 团粉 汤
Sugar, Chinese cooking wine, MSG, starch (which is used for thickening), soup
# 二是制作方法
Second, cooking instruction
# 鱼去鳞鳃鳍 开膛去五脏洗净
Remove the scales, gills, fins of the fish. Open up the fish and remove the organs. Clean it well.
# 在鱼身两面斜剞一字刀纹
Create tilted parallel cuts on both sides of fish body.
# 葱姜蒜均切成碎末
Chop green onions, ginger, and garlic.
# 条件有限
We have limited options (e.g. pot size).
# 这鱼你看
Look at this fish
# 只能给切成两半了 没办法
We have to cut it into two pieces. No way to resolve this.
# 它没有过多的调料
It doesn’t have too much seasoning.
# 就是鱼 葱姜蒜
It’s just fish, green onion, ginger, garlic
# 你看这鱼 包括鳃也好 鳍也好
See, you have to remove the scales, gills, fins,
# 全部得铰掉了
…all of them…
# 然后烧热油 将鱼炸到七成熟
Then you would heat up the oil, till the fish is medium well
# 它不是完全炸熟了
Don’t fry it to well done.
# 其实为什么过去的书
So why old books …
# 它写的含金量要高
… have higher writing quality?
# 你别瞧文字简单
The words are simple yet precise.
# 现在的鱼炸的都非常干
The fried fish nowadays tends to be very dry
# 你看烧出鱼里边不嫩
So it lost the tenderness when it is served on the table.
# 它要求你炸七成熟
The book recipe requires you to fry the fish to medium well.
# 这就是烹饪要求
Be aware of this requirement.
# 先不能翻 定住型再翻
Don’t flip until the fish shape is set.
# 这还行 没问题
This looks fine. No problem.
# 书上说 炸至七成熟
The book says, fry it till medium well.
# 七成熟就给它捞出来就得了
So scoop it out when it reaches medium well.
# 行了 然后捞出鱼 留下一些油
Ok. After scooping out the fish, leave some oil in the pot.
# 下入豆瓣酱炒酥
Add in Doubanjiang and fry it till crispy.
# 这个一定要煸酥了它
You have to make it crispy.
# 煸不酥它有臭腥味
Otherwise it will have a gamey taste.
# 煸酥了它又不能煸糊了
But not so much that it is burnt.
# 好 第二步是什么 葱姜蒜
Ok. What’s the second step? Green onion, ginger, and garlic.
# 再下入葱姜蒜炒一下
Add in green onion, ginger, and garlic to fry together.
# 留一部分葱说的是
The book also mentions “leave some green onion”.
# 这你怎么掌握那么清楚啊
Oh you seem to know this very well.
# 我看着书呢师父
I am reading out the book now, master.
# 留下一些葱
Leave some green onion.
# 加入汤 酱油 糖 料酒
Add in soup, soy sauce, sugar, Chinese cooking wine.
# 料酒 酱油
Chinese cooking wine, soy sauce.
# 白胡椒粉
White pepper powder.
# 再来点糖 糖别太多
Some more sugar, but not too much.
# 加开水
Add boiling water
# 把鱼放入锅内 先烧它一会
Put the fish back to the pot and leave it there for a while.
# 师父这个烧多长时间
How long does it take?
# 烧的把这汁
Till the liquid…
# 基本上㸆去多一半
…becomes almost half of the original volume.
# 看看颜色
Watch the color.
# 剩下的汁能打上芡就够了
Cook till the rest of the liquid is enough for starch to thicken.
# 咱们怎么着也得烧个二十分钟
It will take at least 20 minutes, I think.
# 师父 咱们这鱼二十分钟了
Master, the fish has been cooked for 20 minutes.
# 差不多了 好了
Almost done, ok.
# 吃的就是这火候
Timing is everything.
# 走
Take and go!
# 收汁 最后一步 料渣篦出去
Thicken the liquid. Last step is to leave the dregs out.
# 收汁咱们按照它的要求
Let us follow the instruction.
# 出勺时 加入醋和一些油
Before thickening the liquid, add in some vinegar and oil.
# 来点醋 来点味精 少来点味精
Some vinegar, some MSG, just a little bit.
# 下入味精 （用淀粉）勾芡
Add slurry to thicken the liquid.
# 你看 拉长线
Look, I can make a long and smooth waterfall.
# 让它熬的起了泡了
Heat it till bubbling.
# 来点油 葱油
Add in some oil (scallion oil)
# 我们得来点葱花 这点睛之笔
We have to put in some chopped green onion as a finishing touch.
# 最后来点葱花 这就行了
In the end, some chopped green onion, that’s it.
# 这个不但是能烧鳜鱼
This recipe works not just for Mandarin fish, …
# 草鱼 鲤鱼 鲈鱼全行是吧
… but also for grass carp, carp, bass, etc.
# 什么鱼都行
Works for any fish
# 这芡够亮
The Qian (thickened sauce) is bright enough.
# 然后最后它有一个注解
Finally, the recipe has a footnote.
# 此菜要求吃出酸甜辣咸各味
A successful making will give the tastes of sour, sweet, spicy, salty and more.
# 活鱼可不用油炸
One could skip the frying step for fresh fish.
# 只用少许的油两面煎一下就可以了
Fry in shallow oil on both sides of the fish is just fine.
# 特点 鱼肉鲜嫩
The characteristic is the tenderness and xian (umami) of the fish.
# 口味辣中带甜酸 四川名菜之一
The taste is spicy hinted with sweetness and sourness. One of the famous Sichuan dishes.
# 今天为什么把这个菜谱念一念
Why are we reading the recipes today?
# 我记得我老师上学的时候
I remember when I was in school, …
# 我老师跟我说的一句话
… my teacher once told me that...
# 你既然选择了烹饪这一行
… now that you choose to pursue a career in culinary art, …
# 那你就选择了付出
… you have to prepare to give”…
# 你就从今以后你选这行
In your future career, …
# 你就没有休息日了
… you don’t have any day off.
# 等我们离开岗位的时候
Now we retire from our roles, …
# 要做一些事情的时候
… and do something else.
# 其实就是凭我们
Speaking from the perspective of our …
# 这么多年的这些经验来讲
… years of experience, …
# 要传给后人
We ask ourselves on what to pass on.
# 其实当我特别是看到社会现象
In fact, when I observe the society, …
# 有一些不好的现象
… when I noticed some bad phenomenon.
# 比如说这么大盘的菜
For example, when I saw a huge plate …
# 这么一丢丢点东西
… placed with just a tiny little food,
# 对我们行业有误解 有曲解的意思
I think there might be a misunderstanding, or misinterpretation of our profession.
# 所以说我跟大爷要尽我所能
So, Da Ye and I agree to do what we can
# 要把这份传承要传承好
To pass on the legacy we are proud of.
# 我们老饭骨
Us Lao Fan Gu,…
# 在这条路上已经走了两年了
… has been doing this for 2 years.
# 我相信在今后的道路上
I believe in the future, …
# 不管有多难 我们要走下去
… no matter how hard it is gonna be, we promise to carry on our mission…
# 要坚守这个东西
… to preserve the culinary legacy.
# 是不是大爷 好
What do you say, Da Ye? Yes.
# 给二伯鼓掌 谢谢师父
Give a round of claps to Er Bai. Thank you master!
# 一般二伯那些书 大爷那些书
In normal days, if Er Bai and Da Ye …
# 说如果今天不拿出来
… don’t bring out the books, …
# 可能大家永远也见不到
… we could never see it.
# 没有老饭骨的呈现
Without Lao Fan Gu’s effort,
# 大家可能也听不到一些
… people may not have the chance to hear…
# 老饭骨背后的故事
…the stories behind.
# 还有一些菜的故事
And the stories about the dishes.
# 我有时候常跟隋坡说
Sometimes I often discuss with Sui Po that
# 我们是耍手艺的
.. we are people who live on craftmanship.
# 我曾经也说过
I used to say that…
# 你看中国有四大手艺人
… there are 4 types of craftsmanship in China,…
# 其中一个手艺人就是我们厨师
… one of them is us chef/cook.
# 另外我们老饭骨
In addition, us Lao Fan Gu,…
# 还要继续的走下去
… will keep going.
# 工匠精神是坚持下来的
Craftmanship becomes durable only when we keep doing what we do.
# 不是说说下来了 是干出来的
Action speaks louder than words.
# 今天为了（感谢）
To thank
# 小饭骨们这一年多来的表现
Xiao Fan Gu’s effort in the past years,
# 今天大爷发个小奖
Da Ye has a small prize to give out.
# 谢谢大爷
Thank you Da Ye.
# 天儿凉了
The weather becomes colder and colder.
# 谢谢师父
Thank you Master.
# 温暖要送到每个人的身上
I want to make sure everyone stays cozy.
# 谢谢大爷
Thank you Da Ye
# 亲自发 还有我一个
You hand out the prize in person. I have one too?
# 有 必须有
Yep, that is a must.
# 谢谢大爷
Thank you Da Ye.
# 今天来者都有 来者有份
Everyone who comes today gets one.
# 隋坡 来了师父 谢谢
Sui Po. I am coming master, thank you.
# 你看大爷想的多周到啊
Da Ye is so thoughtful.
# 金汤佛跳墙滋补火锅 看见没有
The Nutritious Golden soup Fo Tiao Qiang Hotpot. Did you see?
# 那边的鲍鱼 海参
The abalones, sea cucumbers
# 我们的金汤
Our golden soup
# 看这海参
Look at the sea cucumbers.
# 全是大海参 大鲍鱼
All huge abalones and sea cucumbers.
# 还有这么多羊肉
So much lamb meat as well.
# 虾 鱼丸 虾丸 鱼片
Shrimp, fish ball, shrimp ball, fish fillet.
# 还有这边的烧饼 羊肉片
And the Shaobing, lamb slices,
# 还有各种素菜 配上金汤
And a variety of vegetables, with golden soup.
# 那吃的美美的
Beautiful and Satisfying.
# 老饭骨团建 彩
Lao Fan Gu Team Building. Perfect!
# 干杯
Cheers!